Julius Seelye Bixler Papers, 1926-1969
Smith College Archives
Julius Seelye Bixler Papers
1926-1969
Bixler, Julius Seelye, 1894-
RG 42 UUID:78e49dc7-164f-4825-a0e2-f761cc965fd0
1 box (.45 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of Religion at Smith College and later President of Colby College. Contains correspondence, biographical information, lecture notes, photographs, publications and writings spanning Bixler's career.
Biographical Note
Smith College Assistant Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature, 1924-25
Associate Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature, 1925-29
Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature, 1929-33
Julius Seelye Bixler was born on April 4, 1894, in New London, CT, to James William Bixler and Elizabeth J. Seelye Bixler. His father was a clergyman who was elected to the New Hampshire House of Representatives and Senate. His maternal grandfather, Julius Seelye, was president of Amherst College from 1876-90, and his grand uncle was L. Clark Seelye, the first president of Smith College. J. Seelye Bixler attended the Classical High in New London, where he played football. He matriculated at Amherst College with the class of 1916, where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, the senior honorary society "Scarab," won first prize in the commencement speaking contest, was song leader for his class, and also was a member of the Alpha Delta Pi fraternity.
After his graduation from Amherst in 1916, he became an instructor of Latin and English at the American College in Madura India for a year, before returning to the States to attend Union Theological Seminary in New York. In September of 1917 he married Mary Harrison Thayer, Smith College class of 1917. During World War I, he served in the army until December of 1918. He soon returned to Amherst College for graduate study in the spring of 1919, and the following school year served as Director of Religious Activities, while completing the requirements for an MA, which he received from Amherst in 1920.
In 1920 Bixler became a lecturer at the American University in Beirut, Syria, which is where the first of his four daughters, Mary Harriet, (Smith College '42) was born. In 1922, he returned to the United States to study at Yale, and the following year conducted research at Harvard for his thesis on William James before returning to Yale to receive his Ph.d. in 1924. Bixler received honorary degrees from many institutions. In 1924 he became a member of the Smith College faculty, acting as Assistant Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature from 1924- 25, Associate Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature, 1925- 29 and Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature, 1929-33. From 1928-29, Bixler took a leave of absence to study and conduct research at the University of Freiberg, Germany. In 1933, he became Bussey Professor of Theology at Harvard, a position that he held until 1942, when he accepted the position of President of Colby College, which he held for 18 years.
As president of Colby College, his achievements included relocating the campus from downtown Waterville to a 900 acre site on the edge of the town, as well as building 27 new campus buildings, more than doubling the numbers of faculty and students, increasing the endowment from $1 million to $8.5 million, and increasing the annual budget from $400,000 to $2.5 million. He also founded both the art and music departments.
After stepping down from his position of president in 1960, Bixler became a visiting lecturer for the State Department and also helped to set up a liberal arts program at Thammasart University in Bangkok in 1962. He has published extensively, including six books, numerous pamphlets and brochures, essays, contributions to books and periodicals.
Bixler died of pneumonia at the age of 90, on March 28, 1985 at his daughter's home in Weston, MA.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Julius Seelye Bixler Papers contain publications spanning Bixler's career. The publications are on the topics of religion, biblical literature and philosophy ranging in date from 1926 through 1969 and two undated publications.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Julius Seelye Bixler Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Search Terms
Bixler, Julius Seelye, 1894-; Smith College--Faculty.
Additional Information
Bibliography
Religion in the Philosophy of William James, 1926
Immortality and the Present Mood, 1931
Religion for Free Minds, 1939
Conversations with an Unrepentant Liberal, 1946
A Faith that Fulfills, 1951
Education for Adversity, 1952
- Colby College 1941-1960 (Box 681, Folder 1)
- Biographical Information 1927-1985 (Box 681, Folder 2)
- Correspondence 1928, 1933, 1969, n.d. (Box 681, Folder 3)
- Courses n.d. (Box 681, Folder 4)
- Lectures 1929-1934 (Box 681, Folder 5)
- Photographs 1019-1980 (Box 681, Folder 6)
- Publications (Box 682)
- "Albert Schweitzer" 1962 (Box 682)
- "Albert Schweitzer's Unity of of Life & Thought 1960 (Box 682)
- "Best Things in Worst Times" 1943 (Box 682)
- "Can the Campus be a Democracy?" 1968 (Box 682)
- "Can Religion Become Empirical?" in Nature of Religious Experience 1937 (Box 682)
- "Changes in Education Aims Needed after the War" c1943 (Box 682)
- "Contribution of Existenz-Philosophie" 1940 (Box 682)
- "Deeper Ranges of Authority" 1949 (Box 682)
- "Dialogue in Limbo" 1935 (Box 682)
- Education for Adversity 1952 (Box 682)
- "Education for Hardship" 1958 (Box 682)
- "Experiment in Undergraduate Thinking" 1957 (Box 682)
- "Failure of Martin Heidegger" 1963 (Box 682)
- Faith that Fulfills 1951 (Box 682)
- Four Approaches to Belief, 1-4 1956 (Box 682)
- "Humanities and the Open Door to Faith" 1958 (Box 682)
- "Ideas of God as Affected by Modern Thought" 1950 (Box 682)
- Immortality and the Present Mood 1931 (Box 682)
- Josiah Royce-Twenty Years After 1936 (Box 682)
- Letters from Dr. A. Schweitzer in The Colby Library 1964 (Box 682)
- Religion in the Philosophy of William James 1926 (Box 683, Folder 1)
- Professor Dewey Discusses Religion 1930 (Box 683, Folder 2)
- Men and Tendencies in German Religious Thought 1930 (Box 683, Folder 3)
- The Mystic and His Absolutes 1935 (Box 683, Folder 4)
- The Spirit and the Life:A Dialogue 1937 (Box 683, Folder 5)
- The Skeptical Revolt 1937 (Box 683, Folder 6)
- Religion for Free Minds 1939 (Box 683, Folder 7)
- Two Questions Raised by William James' Essay on the Moral Equivalent of War 1942 (Box 683, Folder 8)
- The Problem of Religious Knowledge 1942 (Box 683, Folder 9)
- Science, Materialism and the Human Spirit 1949 (Box 683, Folder 10)
- Reflections on the Art of Teaching 1951 (Box 683, Folder 11)
- Old Salzburg and New World 1951 (Box 683, Folder 12)
- Reappraisals: The Existentialists and William James 1958 - 1959 (Box 683, Folder 13)
- Notes on the Education of a College President 1961 (Box 683, Folder 14)
- What is American in American Philosophy 1963 (Box 683, Folder 15)
- The Two Blessings of Joseph (Honors Convocation Address) 1964 (Box 683, Folder 16)
- On Being Absurd! 1969 (Box 683, Folder 17)
- Productive Tensions in the Work of Albert Schweitzer n. d. (Box 683, Folder 18)
- The Resources of Religion and the Aims of Higher Education n. d. (Box 683, Folder 19)